Această poveste este o operă de ficțiune. Numele personajelor, organizațiilor și ale celorlalte elemente menționate sunt fictive. De asemenea, nu există legături cu evenimente reale.
Is this authentic?
Desigur.
Ai devenit și mai frumoasă?
Episodul 25: Maomao și Maomao
Ce e această grămadă
uriașă, bunico?
Se pare că a fost
comandată de Maomao.
Din nou?
This'll be a good business.
Just deliver it like you're told.
Am înțeles.
They're beautiful.
I'm thinking of keeping some in my room.
E totul în regulă?
D-Da.
După petrecerea din grădină, stăpânul Shishou
a cerut mai multe slujitoare pentru ea.
Dar asta e deja exagerat...
Da. Nu arată prea bine
pentru celelalte concubine.
Bună, concubină Loulan.
Oh? Cauți ceva anume?
Oh, nu.
Maomao e la clinică.
Chiar a venit primăvara.
Ce meșterești?
De ce mă întrebi de
parcă aș face ceva greșit?
Fac uleiuri parfumate.
În timp ce curățam clinica,
am găsit un distilator.
Și folosesc câteva din florile rămase de la trandafirii
albaștri pe care am reușit să-i cultivăm.
Mirosul e foarte puternic.
Și tot nu e la fel de puternic
ca al trandafirilor sălbatici.
Cu ce te pot ajuta?
Oricine și-ar face griji dacă ar
simți un miros atât de puternic.
Lucrezi aici deoarece nu ai tot
ce-ți trebuie la Pavilionul de Jad?
Și asta, dar...
Unele uleiuri parfumate
pot provoca avorturi.
Nu ar trebui să fie o problemă decât
dacă sunt foarte concentrate, dar...
Deci nu e nevoie să interzicem parfumurile și
alte lucruri de genul în palatul interior, nu?
Da. Nu ar trebui să fie o problemă.
Doctorul gogoman e de treabă,
dar nu știe să-și țină gura.
Nu ar trebui să afle încă despre
sarcina concubinei Gyokuyou.
Ce e asta?
Alcool distilat.
Prin distilări repetate,
pot crea un alcool foarte puternic.
Și plănuiești să-l bei?!
E pentru dezinfectat.
Vreau ca Pavilionul de Jad
să fie cât mai curat posibil,
deoarece avem o prințesă micuță.
Poți face așa ceva?
Înmoi cârpa în asta și
ștergi suprafețele și alte lucruri.
Știi foarte multe lucruri.
Am auzit că această metodă
se folosește în vest.
Oh, așa este. Tatăl tău adoptiv este...
Am adus un pachet.
Ce este?
Ah, the little lady—
Stăpâne Jinshi, voi pregăti niște ceai.
Vă rog să luați un loc.
Ce e în el?
Acest pachet este de la familia mea.
Nu e nimic important!
Oh, de la familia ta?
Care-i problema acestui tip?!
E-Este... lenjerie intimă.
Oh... Înțeleg.
Dar din ce e făcută lenjeria intimă dacă
e nevoie de doi oameni să care pachetul?
Problema palatului interior este că
se așteaptă ca femeile să fie foarte
inocente în privința actul sexual.
Majoritatea slujitoarelor
aduse sunt virgine.
Dacă împăratul găsește o fată pe placul lui,
iar ea nu se descurcă
din cauza ignoranței?
Așa că m-am gândit că ar
trebui instruite dinainte.
Și... de asta ai adus astea aici?
Books, like the ones from
back then. You know, then.
After all the work I did to get them
delivered to the clinic,
out of Lady Hongniang's sight...
I used to order them for the emperor,
who loves these,
but I increased the order to get more business.
Bad timing, though.
Aceste cărți...
These books...
sunt foarte bine făcute.
are very well made.
Hârtia este de calitate.
The paper is of high quality.
Asta a observat? Credeam
că e un pervers în secret.
That's what he noticed? I thought
maybe he was a closet pervert.
These books are sometimes used
as part of a new bride's package,
and it's popular because the pictures are
enough to enjoy, even if you can't read.
A print.
Not woodblock prints,
but ones that use metal plates.
Impresionant.
That's impressive.
Yes. Because it's so good, I wanted
as many people to see it as possible.
That's a separate issue.
If you find this to your liking,
perhaps you should keep one?
N-No! That's definitely not it!
I guess I can let you
off the hook this one time.
Serios?!
Really?!
Spune-mi ce magazin le vinde.
Tell me which shop sells these.
Nu e ce crezi! Vreau doar
să aflu cum le tipăresc!
No! I just want to know
about their printing techniques!
Da, sigur. Vrei să
știi magazinul, nu?
Yes, of course. The shop, got it.
Xiaomao.
Da?
What is it?
Cred că va fi nevoie să
cenzurăm cărțile mai explicite.
Perhaps some of the more
explicit ones need to be censored.
But the emperor said the previous ones
weren't exciting enough, so—
Nu.
No.
Mare păcat... Mai ales după ce i-am cerut
bunicii să le aleagă pe cele mai bune...
Sigh... And after I asked Granny to do
all that work to pick the best ones...
Vai, ce sper să găsesc
sub florile albastre?
Oh, what is it that I seek,
beneath those beautiful flowers?
Hei, ce crezi că e îngropat acolo?
Hey, what do you think is buried there?
Ce?
Huh.
Bălegar?
Manure?
Mănânci prea repede.
You ate too quickly.
Nu, e vina ta!
No, it's your fault!
Hei, acest roman e foarte popular!
This novel is really popular, you know!
Știi să citești, Xiaolan?
Can you read, Xiaolan?
Nu! Dar una dintre fetele care
știu ni-l citește cu voce tare.
Nope! But one of the girls
who can is reading it out loud for us.
Vreau să aflu cum se continuă!
I want to know the rest!
If even the illiterate
servant girls know the story,
the book must truly be popular.
M-am întors.
I'm back.
Ce este?
What is that?
Împăratul l-a dat fiecărei concubine.
The emperor handed it out
to all of the concubines.
A spus că ar trebui să-l arate și
celorlalți după ce termină de citit.
He said once they're done reading it,
they should show the others, as well.
Vrei și tu să-l citești, Maomao?
Do you want to read it too, Maomao?
Se pare că e același despre care
vorbea și Xiaolan. Un roman popular.
Looks like it's the same as the one
Xiaolan talked about. A popular novel.
These are considered low class
in high society. So I wonder why...
Hmm? This stamp...
It's from the place I told
Master Jinshi about the other day.
It might be a novel, but it's of a high
quality, befitting a gift from the emperor.
If he gave it out to all of the concubines,
there must be at least one hundred copies.
Master Jinshi must have
asked the emperor to do it.
Wow! What a page-turner! I can't stop!
I should have charged a commission!
But why? Novels are considered lowly.
Why hand it out to concubines of noble birth...
I knew it had to do with politics.
He really was scheming something.
Oh no, I finished it!
Vreau să aflu cum se continue!
I want to read the rest!
Gaoshun a spus că ni-l va da
pe următorul când va fi gata.
Master Gaoshun said he'll hand out
the next one when they're ready.
S-a întâmplat ceva?
Is something wrong?
Ei bine, noi suntem singurele
slujitoare de la Pavilionul de Jad, nu?
Well, we're the only ladies-in-waiting
at the Jade Pavilion, right?
It feels like a waste, having a gift from
Lady Gyokuyou like this enjoyed by just us.
But we can't hand it out to the girls
outside the pavilion. It's too precious.
Dacă l-ar pierde?
What if they lost it?
Ai dreptate.
You're right.
Instead of handing out the originals,
you could create copies yourself.
Maybe the pictures are too difficult,
but Lady Ailan, your penmanship is excellent.
It shouldn't be a problem
for you to make copies.
Y-You think so?
Yikes, that sounds like a lot of work!
Nu spune asta, Yinghua!
Yinghua, don't say that!
This is probably the correct
interpretation of Master Jinshi's idea.
Haide să încercăm.
Let's give it a try.
De unde ar trebui să începem?
Where should we start?
If books became popular in the rear palace,
mulți vor dori să învețe să citească,
many will want to try to learn to read,
mai ales dacă e vorba
de un roman popular.
especially if the book is a popular novel.
Back when I was Master Jinshi's
servant, he did ask me...
Apothecary, what do you think we can do to
improve the literacy rate of the court ladies?
Still, he chose a very
roundabout way of doing it.
Hei, Maomao!
Hey, Maomao!
Învață-mă, te rog,
să scriu și să citesc!
Please teach me how to read and write!
Where'd that come from?
Fata care ne citea romane
a răgușit de la prea mult vorbit.
The girl who read the novels out loud for us
wore out her voice by reading too much.
În schimb, ne-a făcut copii la cărți,
dar eu nu știu să citesc.
Instead, she made copies of
the books for us, but I can't read.
Atunci, ți l-aș putea citi eu—
Then I could read them to you—
Nu!
No!
That girl spent so much time making
copies for me. I can't cheat like that.
Good girl.
Hey, what's this, all of a sudden?!
Acesta e numele tău.
Încearcă să-l scrii și tu.
This is your name. Try to write it yourself.
Bine!
Got it!
Nu știam că numele meu
era așa de complicat.
I didn't know my name was so complicated.
Writing helps you learn to read too,
but do you want to just focus on reading?
Nu, aș vrea să învăț și să scriu!
No, I might as well learn to write, too!
Once I leave the rear palace,
I have to work on my own.
Being able to read and write helps, right?
Ce e asta?!
What is this?!
Xiaolan se gândește la viitorul ei.
Xiaolan is thinking about
her future in her own way.
Let's go a bit quickly, then.
Da, doamnă!
Yes, thank you!
Ce ai scris acolo?
What does this say?
Mushroom fungus.
And this?
Ciumăfaie.
Thornapple.
This?
Rădăcini de Kudzu.
Kudzu root.
Hey, are those commonly used words?
We should start with greetings.
Sună bine.
Sounds good.
Prințesa Lingli are voie
să iasă la plimbare acum?
Is Princess Lingli allowed to go on walks now?
Da. Pavilionul a devenit puțin cam mic
pentru ea, așa că am cerut permisiunea.
Yes. The pavilion has become
a bit too small for her, so I asked.
Chiar îi place să alerge peste tot.
She really likes to run around
all over the place.
Tu ce părere ai, Maomao?
What do you think, Maomao?
I agree. For the princess's health, it would
be best for her to go outside more.
Two eunuchs will follow her as guards.
Could you and Hongniang accompany her?
Desigur.
Understood.
All of the emperor's previous children
have passed away very young.
This seems like a bit of
an overreaction for a simple walk,
but I guess it's understandable.
Maomao, you know a lot about
flowers and creatures.
Can you teach Lingli while we're outside?
Lady Gyokuyou, no! She'll teach
the princess all sorts of nasty things.
Oh? I think it's useful.
Cine știe unde se va mărita?
Who knows where she'll get married off?
The princess is still a baby, but in
a decade or so, talks of marriage may arise.
If she went to a foreign nation,
she might not necessarily be welcome.
Knowing about medicines
and poisons can only help her.
Chiar e o concubină inteligentă.
She really is a clever concubine.
Reactions to seeing the princess are varied.
They represent the differing
views towards her.
Perhaps soon, she'll learn
what those eyes mean.
Aceea e o primulă.
That's a primrose.
Oh, Princess!
Princess!
Princess! You mustn't!
I'll go take a look.
O pisicuță?
A kitten?
Prințesă!
Princess!
Trebuie s-o prind?
I have to catch it?
Of, fie.
Oh, well.
Te-am găsit!
Found you!
Vrei pisicuța?
You want this?
Oh, credeam că încerci s-o prinzi.
M-am înșelat cumva?
Oh, I thought you were
trying to catch it. Was I wrong?
Mulțumesc.
Thank you.
Poftim.
Here.
S-ar putea să-i fie foame.
O voi lăsa în grija ta!
It might be hungry. I'll leave it to you!
Ne mai vedem!
See ya!
Maomao, aia este...
Maomao, is that...
Da, o pisică.
Yes, a cat.
E murdară. Micuța prințesă nu
ar trebui s-o atingă deocamdată.
It's dirty. The princess
shouldn't touch it for now.
D-Da...
R-Right...
Let's keep it safe for the time being.
I'll let management know.
Da.
Yes.
Oh, how rare. A kitten.
I found it.
How sad. It's trembling.
I just boiled some water. Hold on a moment.
Dar e ciudat.
This is strange, though.
There are almost no pets in the rear palace.
Ai nevoie de un permis
ca să deții un animal,
Keeping an animal requires a permit,
iar pisicile și câinii trebuie castrați.
and cats and dogs need to be castrated.
De unde a apărut aceasta pisicuță?
Where was this kitten born?
Wrap a bottle of hot water with cloth,
and put it next to it.
You seem to be familiar with this.
I found a cat before, too.
It was a very cute calico.
Înțeleg.
I see.
E foarte slabă. Avem
cumva niște lapte animal?
It's very skinny. Do we
have any livestock milk?
Voi merge să întreb la bucătărie.
Sure, I'll go ask the kitchen.
Și niște intestine.
Also, a livestock intestine.
I-Intestine?!
I was thinking of using it as
a replacement for its mother's teat.
We had sausages a few times,
perhaps there's some in the kitchen...
Bine, voi merge să întreb.
Sure, I'll go ask.
It would have been best
to bathe it in warm water,
dar în starea ei actuală,
nu v-a supraviețui.
but in its current state, it won't survive.
Instead, I'll have to wipe off
the dirt with a cloth,
and kill any fleas with oil.
Little lady, am găsit lapte de capră!
Little lady, I found some goat milk!
Și niște intestine.
And some intestine, too.
Mersi.
Thank you.
E așa de drăguță.
E așa de drăguță!
So cute. So cute!
That night, the emperor
visited the Jade Pavilion.
Am decis să păstrăm pisica.
We've decided to keep the kitten.
Do continue to take care of it.
The emperor can be a doting parent, too.
Maomao, taking care of a kitten.
It suits your name, too.
When the kitten grew healthier,
I washed it with a detergent
made of crushed soap beans.
Uau, apa s-a făcut gri.
Wow, the water went grey.
I fed it milk for a while,
but as it improved,
it started to be able to eat shredded chicken.
When we put down a box filled with
sand, it relieved itself on its own.
We can't have you scratching the princess.
Cum merge creșterea copilului?
How goes the child-raising?
Cred că e pregătită să-i
fie arătată micuței prințese.
I think she's ready to be
presented to the princess.
Bun.
Good.
Small fish? They might be a bit
tough as-is. Shall I boil them?
O-Of course.
E femelă.
She's female.
Da. Mă bucur că nu
trebuie s-o castrăm—
Yes. I'm glad we don't have to castrate—
Îmi cer scuze.
My apologies.
E în regulă.
Nu-ți face griji.
No, don't worry about it.
Let me get you a snack as an apology...
Can't put these out, I guess.
Vrei să încerci?
You want to try?
Nu-mi plac pisicile.
I don't actually like cats.
Deși te cheamă Maomao?
With your name?
Mi se spune des.
I get that a lot.
Stăpâne Jinshi, văd că-ți plac pisicile.
Master Jinshi, you seem to like cats.
Nu la fel de mult precum celor doi.
Not as much as those two.
Nu prea înțeleg ce-i
fascinează așa de tare.
I don't really understand the appeal.
De acord. Dar potrivit
iubitorilor de pisici,
I agree. However, according to cat lovers,
faptul că nu înțelegi ce gândesc
face parte din farmecul lor.
the fact that you can't tell what
they're thinking is part of the appeal.
Oh.
E distractiv să le privești.
Nu-ți poți lua ochii de la ele.
They're fun to watch. You can't
keep your eyes off of them.
After a while, you start
to want to touch them.
Hm...
Hmm.
They usually behave coldly,
but suddenly become friendly
when you feed them, which is annoying.
Bezoar de bivol
Î-Înțeleg...
R-Right...
At that point, they say
you just kind of give up.
Poking at their paws, kissing them...
it all seems very unsanitary.
Ce s-a întâmplat, stăpâne Jinshi?
What's wrong, Master Jinshi?
Cred că încep să înțeleg și eu.
I'm starting to see it, too.
Serios?
Is that so?
Nu au reușit să afle de
unde a venit pisicuță,
They never figured out
where the kitten came from,
deci au presupus că s-ar fi strecurat
înăuntru cu un cărucior de bagaje.
so they assumed she must have
snuck in with a luggage cart.
Apoi, pisicuța...
Later, the kitten...
a primit din partea împăratului
titlul de „Admonisher of Thieves”.
was bestowed the title of
"Admonisher of Thieves" by the emperor.
Altfel spus, a primit sarcina de a vâna
șobolanii care amenințau magazia clinicii.
In other words, she was tasked with chasing
down rats threatening the clinic's reserves.
Maomao
Dar...
I9KE3ewJDbVXpTN3!
:!iLu65K530KHfJsy
Dl8"Vl2vr"ydfBUWc
Pf!:s;n0iANpp"NUC
hEVhz0qK.aBh!EQrM
zZbL7"uMpxtkkVl"C
Nu voi înțelege niciodată de ce
au ales să-i pună numele Maomao.
Haide să terminăm
odată cu curățatul.
Let's get this cleaned up fast.
Da. Vine caravana.
Caravana?
Data viitoare
Data viitoare: „Caravana”.
Episodul 26: Caravana